A Finding Aid to the Charles FitzGerald Scrapbooks, circa 1901-1918, in the Archives of American Art AAA.fitzchar
Archives of American Art
Charles FitzGerald scrapbooks
circa 1901-1918
AAA.fitzchar
Archives of American Art
1.1 Linear feet
Six scrapbooks of art critic Charles FitzGerald measure 1.1 linear feet and date from circa 1901 to 1918. They are comprised of newspaper clippings from the Evening Sun, Sun, New York Times, and other newspapers. Many of the printed articles, except where noted, were written by FitzGerald. Miscellaneous letters to FitzGerald are interleaved within the books and additional loose letters, writings, newspaper clippings, and notes are found. Also included are note cards that contain an index to Scrapbooks #4-6.
Fitzgerald, Charles
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Charles FitzGerald scrapbooks were donated in 1964 by Ira Glackens, FitzGerald's nephew, and in 2007 by Susan Corn Conway. Glackens was the son of portrait painter William Glackens and Edith Glackens; Edith's sister, Irene Dimock FitzGerald was married to Charles. Conway purchased the Glackens' house where additional scrapbooks were located.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The collection was digitized in 2014 and is available on the Archives of American Art's website. Blank pages have not been scanned.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Art critic Charles FitzGerald (1873-1958) lived and worked in New York City, New York and was known for his articles promoting Ash Can school artists. As a writer for the New York Evening Sun and the New York Sun newspapers, FitzGerald frequently published critiques of the National Academy of Design, Society of American Artists, and other conventional art and institutions of his day. In 1915, he married Irene Dimock, whom he had met eleven years prior at the wedding of his close friends, the painter William Glackens and his wife, Edith Dimock Glackens.
Scope and Contents note
Six scrapbooks of art critic Charles FitzGerald measure 1.1 linear feet and date from circa 1901 to 1918. They are comprised of newspaper clippings from the Evening Sun, Sun, New York Times, and other newspapers. Many of the printed articles, except where noted, were written by FitzGerald. Miscellaneous letters to FitzGerald are interleaved within the books and additional loose letters, writings, newspaper clippings, and notes are found. Also included are note cards that contain an index to Scrapbooks #4-6.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 1 series.
Series 1: Charles FitzGerald scrapbooks, circa 1901-1918 (1.1 linear feet; Boxes 1-4)
Art criticism--New York (State)--New York; Art critics--New York (State)--New York; Scrapbooks
- Charles FitzGerald Scrapbooks, circa 1901-1918; Series 1; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-4
  Scope and Contents note
  The six scrapbooks consist of clippings from the Evening Sun, Sun, New York Times, and other newspapers. Many of the articles, except where noted, were written by Fitzgerald. Topics include art, current events, education, medicine, the Navy, and war.
  A handful of miscellaneous letters to Fitzgerald are interleaved within the books along with additional loose letters, writings, miscellaneous newspaper clippings on sculptures and photographic processes, and essay notes on works by old masters. Also included are cards that contain a subject index to Scrapbooks #4-6.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Correspondence, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Writings, circa 1901-1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Clippings relate to wax bust by Leonardo da Vinci.
  - Clippings, Miscellaneous, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notecard Index to Scrapbooks #4-6, circa 1901-1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook #1, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook #2, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook #3, 1903-1904 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook #4, 1901-1913 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook #5, 1904-1906 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook #6, 1914-1918 (Box 4, Folder 1)